SHEKHAR SINGH

Mechatronics Engineering Graduate

ssingh@optisolutions.co.za
LinkedIn: Shekhar Singh

♀ Cape Town, South Africa **►** +27 81 040 1780



A UCT graduate in Mechatronics Engineering with a background in electromechanical design, and software engineering. Gained experience and training in Electrical and Mechanical engineering. In possession of strong leadership and communication skills due to numerous leadership positions occupied from a young age.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Microsoft AppFactory Intern OptiSolutions

Dec 2020 - Present

 I joined the Microsoft AppFactory internship programme through OptiSolutions, where I've gained more software development experience. Achieved skills in Node, Git/Github, PowerApps, Azure, and app development.

Faculty Tutor

University of Cape Town (EBE Electrical department & EBE Mechanical Department

₩ Feb 2017 - Dec 2020

- Tutored in mechanical and electrical design using various design programmes (including SolidWorks, AutoCAD, Altium Design, and KiCAD). I've also lectured some classes, and in doing so, I've gained teaching experience and further knowledge in each programme.
- Tutored in mechanical and electrical design using various design programmes (including SolidWorks, AutoCAD, Altium Design, and KiCAD). I've also lectured some classes, and in doing so, I've gained teaching experience and further knowledge in each programme.

Academic Researcher

University of Cape Town (EBE Electrical department)

m Dec 2019 - Jan 2020

♀ Cape Town, South Africa

• Worked as a student researcher for a professor in an academic project regarding ultrasonic applications for medical use.

Apprentice

ND Engineering

m Jun 2016 - Aug 2016

 Worked as an apprentice with a group of other university students in which we trained in various departments in the this industrial company. I further developed my skills in fitting, turning and welding, as well as learned new skills in the manufacturing and assembly departments.

Apprentice

Intech Instrumentation

Mov 2015 - Jan 2016

Q Durban, KZN

- I worked under a team of mechanical and instrumental engineers, where I first learned trade skills involving fitting, turning, and welding.
- The company has specialized engineers of various fields, and with the workshop based in the Shell Chemicals PTY LTD plant site, I furthered my knowledge of electrical and instrumentation by working under the electrical team to maintain the electrical aspects of the plant.

SKILLS

PROFESSIONAL: Leadership abilities	3KILL3
Interpersonal skills	PROFESSIONAL:
Problem solving Customer service skills Teamwork skill Communication Adaptability Conflict Resolution Decision making Organization ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Leadership abilities Creativity
Customer service skills Teamwork skill Communication Adaptability Conflict Resolution Decision making Organization ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Interpersonal skills Critical thinking
Communication Adaptability Conflict Resolution Decision making Organization ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Problem solving
Conflict Resolution Decision making Organization ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Customer service skills Teamwork skill
Organization ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Communication Adaptability
ENGINEERING: Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Conflict Resolution Decision making
Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Organization
Welding Fitting Turning PCB design Electronic design Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
PCB design	ENGINEERING:
Mechanical design Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Welding Fitting Turning
Controls System design PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	PCB design Electronic design
PROGRAMMING: C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Mechanical design
C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	Controls System design
C/C++ Embedded Systems Python HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
jQuery MATLAB Node/Express LaTeX SQL SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	C/C++ Embedded Systems Python
SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	HTML/HTML5 CSS Javascript
SOFTWARE: Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	jQuery MATLAB Node/Express
Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	LaTeX SQL
Microsoft Office Suit MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD	
	MATLAB/SIMULINK PowerApps
Fusion360 Adobe Illustrator	Azure SolidWorks AutoCAD
	Fusion360 Adobe Illustrator

HOBBIES:

Adobe Photoshop

Adobe After Effects

Adobe Media Encoder

Autodesk Sketchbook

Photography
Videography

Oraphics design

UX design

Adobe Lightroom

COMMUNITY & VOLUNTEER WORK

Community Outreach

(Various organizations)

2013 - Present

♥ Cape Town & Durban, South Africa

 Volunteered my services in many feeding schemes in different organizations over the years. These organizations include religious and academic societies, outreach programmes at the university, and small charity drives with my family over the festive period.

Animal Rescue

SPCA & LEAPs

Cape Town, South Africa

 At the LEAPS Adoption Agency NGO and the Cape Town SPCA, I've volunteered my services in taking care of the dogs almost every and to promote the adoption of the dogs in the shelters.

EDUCATION

BSc Electrical Engineering (Specialising in Mechatronics) University of Cape Town

₩ 2020

♀ Cape Town, South Africa

Matriculant Pass

Crossmoor Secondary School

2014

Ourban, KZN

Graduated with six (6) distinctions.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- 2018:
 - Chairperson of the UCT Hindu Student's Society
- 2017:
 - Member of MENSA South Africa
 - Sub-committee member of the UCT Hindu Student's Society
- 2016:
 - Class medal for Physics
- 2014:
 - 3rd Academic position award (Crossmoor Secondary School)
 - Deputy Head Prefect
 - Student Council President
 - Graduated from the MMI Mathematics and Physics programme
- 2013:
 - Student council treasury
 - CADSSA Table tennis (District team)
- 2012:
 - · Representative on the student council
 - · Graduated with black belt in Shotokan Karate
 - Invited into the MMI Mathematics and Physics programme

LANGUAGES

English Afrikaans Hindi



REFEREES

Mr. Julian Kanjere Supervisor, AppFactory Team

- OptiSolutions
- **4** +27 76 333 5338

Mrs. Charmaine Findeis Lecturer, Dept. Mechanical Engineering

- University of Cape Town
- **4** +27 21 650 2068

Mr. Justin Pead Lecturer, Dept. Electrical Engineering

- **Q** University of Cape Town
- **(** -